In my Daily Dozen checklist,
I recommend eating one
tablespoon of flaxseed a day.
But you may have heard
that flaxseed contains cyanide.
What?!
Is it anything to worry about?
Watch the video to find out.
"How Well Does Cooking Destroy Cyanide
in Flax Seeds and Should We Be Concerned?"
Sweden's dietary guidelines
are pioneering in many ways;
for example, encouraging people
to decrease their climate impact
by choosing more plant-based foods,
which tend to produce greatly
fewer greenhouse gas emissions.
But I was surprised by this page
on the official Swedish
National Food Agency website,
which translates to cyanogenic
glycosides and hydrogen cyanide,
encouraging people to stay away
from ground flaxseed
for fear of cyanide toxicity,
as in the ground flax seeds
I encourage everyone
to eat every day.
You can see why this was
the first question I got
when I spoke in Stockholm.
Was the Swedish government
on to something?
Had I just been duped by
Big Flax-funded researchers
who claimed you could eat pounds of
ground flaxseeds a day without worrying,
more than 150 tablespoons a day?
First, some background.
As many as one in five plants
that we eat produce cyanide.
In fact, if you look at the major
food crops in the world,
more than half are cyanogenic,
meaning cyanide producing.
See, unlike toxic elements like lead,
mercury, arsenic that can't be broken
down into anything, cyanide
is an organic molecule:
one carbon atom attached
to one nitrogen atom.
In this state it can definitely be toxic,
but broken down or complexed to
something else and it loses its toxicity.
And we have an enzyme in our
body that does just that,
a cyanide detoxifying enzyme.
And that's just one of five main ways
our body can detoxify cyanide.
It does require protein to do it though,
and so that's why you can read about
chronic cyanide toxicity among
malnourished populations in Africa
trying to live off of improperly
processed cassava root.
But as long as we're getting
adequate protein in our diet,
our body can detoxify the normal
amounts of cyanide we eat every day.
Now there is a rare, congenital genetic
condition called Leber's disease,
where you're born without
the ability to detoxify cyanide.
And indeed, yeah, you could go blind
drinking apple cider or something,
but otherwise our bodies evolved to
be cyanide-detoxifying machines,
but obviously there's a limit.
For example, a case of cyanide
poisoning after bitter almond ingestion.
Not regular almonds, which produce
about 40 times less cyanide,
but bitter almonds, which you can't even
buy—they're used in flavor manufacturing—
but if you did, eating 50
of them could kill you,
or even just a handful
for a small child.
This suggests that eating 2,000
regular almonds at one sitting
could also be bad news.
You can't buy bitter almonds,
but you can buy apricots,
and apricot kernels, which are the
seeds inside the stone, actually have
pretty toxic levels, and have
indeed been implicated in cases
of severe cyanide poisoning,
all linked to the
"Laetrile: cult of cyanide,
Promoting poison for profit"
that I talked about previously.
So I'm totally sympathetic to regulators
wanting to take a precautionary approach.
But are flaxseeds like bitter almonds,
where just a few ounces could kill you,
or more like regular almonds
where regular dietary intake
wouldn't even come close?
Although the fact that flaxseeds
can produce cyanide sounds like
it would be a significant
health concern,
it is not for several reasons, says
flax industry-funded scientists.
First, the adult human body
has the ability to detoxify
up to 100 mg of cyanide per day.
That's where they come up with
their "pounds of flaxseeds
a day are safe" number.
And if you wanted
to eat more than
those totally unrealistic
150 tablespoons a day,
you could just eat them in baked goods
since cooking destroys the cyanide.
And eating 7 or 8 tablespoons
of raw doesn't even bump
urinary thiocyanate levels, which is
an indicator of cyanide exposure,
so it doesn't even look like
your body is even exposed to it.
Thus, the toxicity of flaxseed
from cyanogenic glycosides
is not, evidently,
a realistic health threat.
OK, let's unpack that.
The cooking part is mostly true.
Yes, bake muffins with even
like a quarter cup of ground flax
each for 15 to 18 minutes
at about 450 degrees Fahrenheit and
the cyanide-forming compounds are gone.
Looks like the same thing
happens with baked bread.
But bake ground flax seeds on their
own, and even an hour at 350
only wipes out 20%, though baking
them whole wipes out 80%.
And what, baking in bread
or muffins wipes out 100%?
How does that make any sense?
It's the moisture.
It's heat plus water
that wipes out the cyanide.
Boiling for just five minutes can
wipe it out, like when making
hot cereal or something.
And so, yes, it's true
in most cases
that cooking eliminates
the cyanide compounds
because it typically starts out
in a batter as an egg substitute,
or baking crackers, or the
dough starts out moist.
And so, yes, in those cases the
cyanide is gone upon cooking.
But you can't just spread ground
flaxseeds on a baking sheet
because they dry out so fast that
only a minority of the cyanide is lost.
But, look, why does it
matter if your body
doesn't even seem to notice
7 or 8 tablespoons of raw?
But that's not true.
Urinary thiocyanate
excretion doubled at that level,
though that's just a sign your
body is actively detoxifying it.
And if we can detoxify a kilo worth
of flax a day, what's the problem?
Well, look, even if the adult human
body has the ability to detoxify
up to 100 mg of cyanide a day,
first of all, look, kids eat flax too.
Second of all, a kilo has more than
the 100 you said we could detoxify,
about 50% more.
And I'm not interested in how
much we can detoxify "up to."
For safety you're interested
in the worst-case scenario,
not the best-case scenario.
Would someone please just give
people different doses of flaxseeds
and just measure how much
cyanide ends up in their blood?
But that's never been done until
now, which we'll cover next.
Flaxseeds pack a nutritional punch.
And as a bonus the release
of cyanide from flaxseed
is below a toxic lethal dose.
Well, I should hope so.
Back-of-the-envelope type
calculations have led
industry-funded scientists to assert
that a person would have to consume
8 cups of ground flaxseed at a time
to achieve acute cyanide toxicity.
I'd feel better though if it
was actually put to the test.
Researchers tested flaxseeds under
worst-case scenario conditions,
with respect to resulting in higher
cyanide levels in the blood.
So (1) locate the flaxseed
with the highest level
of cyanide-forming
compounds you can find.
So they went to stores
and bought 15 different sources of
flaxseed, and though the average level
was 140 milligrams per kilo,
which is about typical,
they did find one with 220,
so they used that one.
(2) maximal mechanical destruction
to release the most cyanide.
So they used some crazy
20,000 RPM lab grinder.
(3) eat it all at once
on an empty stomach,
and then keep the stomach empty.
And they gave it raw, since cooking
can often wipe it all out.
If the recommended daily dose
is like one or two tablespoons
of ground flaxseed a day—I recommend
one in my Daily Dozen checklist—
they decided to go with four
and a half tablespoons.
OK, so what happened?
The range of cyanide blood levels
that one might estimate to possibly
be associated with the clinical symptoms
of intoxication would be like 20 to 40.
So that would be like here or higher,
where we want to stay below.
So four and a half tablespoons
on an empty stomach
of the highest cyanide-containing ultra-
ground raw flaxseeds they could find,
and the highest individual
level rise was just under 14,
and the average was down around 6.
There has to be some amount of flax
that takes you over the limit though.
So, they tested 9 tablespoons
and 15 tablespoons too.
Remember, we start to
worry at around 20 to 40.
Three and a half teaspoons of raw high-
cyanide ground flax on an empty stomach?
Hardly a blip.
Seven teaspoons at a time?
Same thing.
Fourteen teaspoons, which is four and
a half tablespoons, and there's that 6.
OK, but what about a little
over 9 tablespoons—
that's over a half cup at a time—
and that does start skirting toxicity.
And finally, what about
a whole cup?
I don't even know how you'd
eat a whole cup at once,
but that is too much, putting you
in that potential toxic range
for about three hours.
So much for the industry's
8 cups at a time are safe.
But even in this worst-case
scenario situation, one cup raw
on an empty stomach at the
highest dose they could find,
that person still didn't actually
have any clinical symptoms.
This is consistent with the fact that
there's not a single published report
of cyanide poisoning after consumption
of flaxseeds anywhere in the literature,
even from Swedish health spas,
where they evidently give up to
12 tablespoons as a fiber shock.
Usually high doses are like two or
so tablespoons three times a day,
and this dose would be safe with respect
to possible acute toxicity of cyanide.
OK, but what about any
possible chronic toxicity?
The World Health Organization
has something called
a PMTDI, the provisional
maximum tolerable daily intake.
It's defined as the amount you
can eat safely, every day,
for the rest of your life,
without risking any adverse
health effects, based on
the best available data,
though often that's just like
rat studies as it was in this case.
If you put varying doses of cyanide
in the drinking water of rats
for a few months, at a certain level,
the so-called benchmark dose
lower confidence limit, there's
a 10% increased incidence
of the shrinkage of the tail of
the epididymis, which is where
sperm is stored in the testicles.
That happens at the human equivalent
of about 150 tablespoons
of flaxseeds a day worth of cyanide.
But they want to err
on the side of caution,
so they introduce a 100-fold uncertainty
factor to create the PMTDI.
So instead of 150 tablespoons
of flaxseeds a day,
the average American should stick
to under 1.5 tablespoons a day,
if you're going to eat
them every day.
So my tablespoon-a-day Daily Dozen
recommendation should be safe
by any of these standards.